today's episode is about the scandal of the diamond necklace so before we get into the
diamond necklace and what it means for mary antoinette for louis xvi and for the french
revolution tell us why you've chosen to kick off with the marriage of figaro and what is going on
so yeah so the marriage of figaro which if people haven't seen the play they may have seen the opera
which was uh adapted by by mozart and it it tells the story of the wedding day of figaro who is the
servant of a lecherous and arrogant spanish count called count alma viva and figaro has just got
married to suzanne who is the maid of the countess the count's wife and the count who is i mean you
know he's he makes louis xv who we had in the previous episode look absolute model of of uh
chastity he wants to exercise the traditional doada senior over suzanne so the right of a lord
to bed whoever
of his dependents he wants to and all kinds of farcical shenanigans ensue dominic love a
farcical shenanigan lots of cross-dressing lots of hiding cupboards jumping out of windows all
kinds of things like that but the plot ends up in a garden by night and the countess and suzanne
have kind of teamed up and they they've got this plan to basically publicly humiliate the count
and kind of get him to reform out of shame and so to that end they've swapped clothes
so that the count will who will mistake his wife the countess for the maid suzanne
and vice versa so it's a kind of classic french farce and figaro is worried that suzanne is
going to sleep with the count even though they've just got married and furious about it
you know he's very upset that the count is behaving like this understandably
and he also thinks that that suzanne is betraying him and so he's assembled a large crowd to catch
and suzanne in flagrante because he thinks this is what's going to happen but it all ends very
happily so because suzanne is very indignant that figaro wouldn't trust it reveals the whole plot to
him the couple are reconciled they have a kiss the count sees them kissing and thinks that figaro is
getting off with his wife the countess absolutely explodes orders them all to be arrested the crowd
summoned by figaro kind of assemble on the stage to you know with flaming torches and everything at
point the countess emerges and reveals who she is the count reveals that the count realizes that
he's been an absolute bounder that he's been tricked and there's a long pause and then he
falls to his knees and begs for forgiveness in the opera i mean it's a stunningly beautiful moment
and the countess does forgive him and everyone is forgiven
and the last line of the plays which is accompanied by music is everything finishes with songs
so there's this idea that the class tensions and the iniquities of the aristocracy can be resolved
with beautiful music but at the time this play by beaumarchais 1784 incredibly controversial
in france because it was seen as so radical in that it was um upturning the social order
there are lots of jokes and remarks and allusions to censorship or the way the justice system works
or the that the fear of being locked up in the bastille yeah um and it's now we just
you know in robert darnton's brilliant book the revolutionary temper there's a whole chapter
about the controversy about the marriage of figaro and how that foreshadows the revolution
yeah and and this is the i i mean people listening to that praise me they're able to keep track of it
they may be wondering how could a farce like this have this kind of incredible reputation i mean it
had it at the time and it had it in the revolution so danton who will be coming to um you know one of
the great revolutionary leaders he says of it it killed off the nobility i mean you might think
it does that but dad says no it's it's the marriage of figaro and napoleon says of the play
because we remember we did the episodes on the young napoleon didn't we he loved to play yeah
and he said that you know this is the revolution in action avola revolution this is what the
revolution is going to become right so the obvious question then if it is as incendiary as contemporary
thought how on earth did it come to be staged and and not only come to be staged but become i mean
unbelievably famous
it kind of in the way that a blockbusting hollywood movie today might be kind of going
completely viral copied parodied so you know the fact that mozart turns it into an opera within
two years of it being premiered is a kind of indication of the cultural cachet that it has
and the celebrity and indeed the notoriety and the truth is that the difficulty of getting it
on stage becomes part of beaumarchais marketing strategy so he he gives the finished grip to the
young napoleon in 1781 and they say yeah this is brilliant so it's the sequel to an earlier play
that had also featured figaro in the count um so they're very keen to put it on but it takes them
three years to get on and the reason for that is that the king is massively offended by it he calls
it detestable and he repeatedly tries to ban it but he reckons without two things and one of them
is beaumarchais himself who is an amazing figure incredibly charismatic extraordinary life um he'd
been a royal agent in london he'd been sent there to protect um madame dubarry from the uh louis
xv's mistress from a libelous pamphlet um he'd had all kinds of dealings with the chevalier deon
who is a diplomat who people think may even have been female but kind of um cross-dresser um
and again kind of cross-dressing is a kind of theme throughout the marriage of figaro
um he ends up running guns to the americans he publishes the complete works of voltaire the great
wit and uh philosoph so an amazing guy and is brilliant at self-publicity and he uses the
censorship battle to publicize the play um and he's able to do this by exploiting what we were
talking about in the previous episode that there are different factions in the court
and lots of the nobility who are opposed to the stuffiness of the king think it's very very funny
yeah to to get the play on and one of the people who thinks it's funny to get the play on
is the queen herself who we talked about the last time who's been behaving in a way that they think
is not suitable for a queen because of her love of the kind of russoist nature and simplicity and
stuff yeah because she's kind of got a girlishness to her uh what a lightness and french queens are
meant to be heavy and she think thinks it's hilarious doesn't she thinks it's really funny
so simon sharma in uh citizen says the more outrageous the denunciations of the established
order the better the queen liked it and that's because the people that she doesn't get on with at
all are the kind of rigid formal old guard kind of people yeah and they're the kind of people to
some degree who don't like this play and are being mocked by it right so she's on naturally on the
side of of lightness and laughter tom absolutely and uh one of the king's brothers um so not the
comte de provence who is the the kind of particularly embittered one but the younger
brother the comte d'artois who's who's very close to marie antoinette i mean he loves it as well he
pushes for it to to be on and so it becomes a massive massive success
esteem not just among you know the ordinary mass of theater goers but among the nobility
and again sharma in his his account of this quotes an aristocrat or yet de freundstein
who describes all the aristocrats in the audience slapping themselves on their own cheeks
laughing at their own expense and even worse making others laugh too a strange blindness
so that's the marriage of figaro but what nobody knows when they're laughing along you know
slapping their cheeks or whatever they're doing what nobody knows is that in just a few weeks
time there will begin an affair scandal that makes the story of the marriage of figaro the
farcical goings-on look humdrum and unfunny and colorless by comparison and this is the beginning
of this tremendous scandal the affair of the diamond necklace tom and this
kicks off i think am i writing saying on the 11th of august 1784. so just a
few months later yeah so the marriage of figaro has premiered in the spring of 1784 and as you
say on the 11th of august something happens an event happens that weirdly echoes the kind of
the climactic scene in the marriage of figaro but kind of as you said ramps it up to to to a
scandalous degree so that evening um a milliner a parisian milliner called nicole legay who has been
used to prostitution by the exactions of loan sharks or so she says is driven to versailles
um and to quote jonathan beckman um who uh is not only a historian but plays cricket with me
in the authors but has i mean i'm not just saying this has written a brilliant account of the whole
scandal how to ruin a queen his description of nicole she was young pretty and broke and with
her broad forehead her straight chiseled nose and her small protuberant mouth
she resembled dominic no one so much as marie antoinette so she gets driven to versailles
and she's greeted there by a woman who calls herself the vicomtesse de valois who tells
nicole something amazing that the queen has personally requested that her nicole do the
queen a favor and that in return nicole will be given fifteen thousand livres which is a lot of
money prostitute um and more than that because she's doing the queen of favor she will be given a
title the vicomtesse de valois says that from this point on nicole will be known as the baron
d'oliva and that is o-l-i-v-a which is kind of an anagram of valois almost an anagram of valois
what are the chances so nicole's suspicions are not aroused by this it has to be said at the time
in fact she's just incredibly bewildered but you know i mean the chance to have a
a title and lots of money yeah why wouldn't you take it what's not to like so the next day she's
stayed at versailles the next day she's dressed in a kind of a plain but expensive white muslin
dress and people who heard our previous episodes will know that this is the kind of signature
costume of marie antoinette yeah herself and she's given a demi bonnet which covers her face
but kind of enables people to see her her lips the vicomtesse then hands uh let's call her d'oliva
because that's now her title a tiny letter uh and says that she is going to to lead her into the
park at versailles she's going to take her to the park at versailles and she's going to take her to
the park at versailles into one of the gardens and that when she gets there um a noble senior
will be waiting and she's to hand this letter over plus a rose and that as she hands the letter
and the rose over she is to say to this senior you know what this means and that's all she has to do
yeah and so at midnight uh the baron d'oliva as she seems to have become is taken out into
the gardens and she is told as she's being led that the queen is watching
her to make sure that she you know does everything that the queen has requested
so um the baron d'oliva nicole aka nicole the impecunious milliner is um
standing in the gardens you know the kind of roses around faint splashing of fountains in
the distance the stars are blazing in the sky and not long afterwards she sees a man approaching her
and this is a man in a long black cassock and a very kind of broad brimmed floppy hat
and he comes up to her and the poor baron is terrified you know she doesn't know who this
person is she's in the royal gardens what's going on but she kind of summons up her courage and she
hands over the rose and she says as she's been instructed to do you know what this means
she's just about to hand over the letter when there's suddenly a kind of an uproar that
sat the torches in the distance the sound of footsteps coming and
arm is grabbed, pulled into the bushes, it's the vicomtesse who's got hold of her, hurries her back,
takes her into her private quarters. And the Baron d'Oliveur, Nicole, apologizes that she
hasn't been able to hand over the letter, but nobody seems to care. Instead, there's a big meal,
the wine flows, and they go to bed. And in the morning, the vicomtesse shows Nicole,
the Baron d'Oliveur, a letter that she has received from Marie Antoinette. And she reads
the letter out. I'm very happy, my dear comtesse, with the person you procured for me. She played
her role to perfection. At this point, the vicomtesse rips up the letter because she says
it is not the kind of letter that one should carry around. So there is no evidence for any of this
that's happened. The vicomtesse then hands over a third of the fee that's been promised. And then
the Baron d'Oliveur is driven back into Paris. From this point on, there is no further reference
to her title. So she goes back to being Nicole.
Nicole, and there is no further money. And that seems to be the end of the matter. I mean, all
very, very strange.
And this is from Nicole's own account, isn't it?
This is from Nicole. Well, it's from the account of her lawyer.
Yeah, everything you're going to hear in this story comes from the accounts given by different
lawyers who would publish, to make money, they would publish memoirs of what their clients had
told them.
But also, Dominic, to be fair, to try and get their clients off.
Yes, of course. So this is Nicole's story. So Tom,
a very kind of Mozart-friendly episode, this.
It's very, very Mozart-friendly.
The Queen looking on, presumably a mysterious suitor in the darkness, the rose is handed over,
all of this kind of thing.
I mean, it's made for an opera.
Yeah. Turn on the lights for us and tell us, first of all, who is that mysterious man in
the cassock that the Queen appears to be giving a rose to?
Well, he is an amazingly important figure in the French noble hierarchy. He's a man called
Louis de Rohin.
And he is a...
He is a messiah of the grandest non-royal family in France. So he traces his lineage
back to the one-time kings of Brittany. And so he has... The Rohin have this phrase,
I cannot be king, I won't be a prince, I am Rohin.
Right.
So, you know, it's better to be Rohin than to be a king or a prince.
Théoden would agree with that, Tom.
Of course, of course. And in his role as...
As a Rohin, he gets to inherit the Bishopric of Strasbourg, which brings with it a cardinalate.
The card... So he becomes, in 1779, he inherits this and he becomes the Cardinal de Rohin.
And in his character, he's very, very... He's a very generous man. But in other ways, I mean,
he's... He's the kind of person who would very easily be taken in by a confidence trickster.
He's basically a cardinal.
He's the kind of character from a sort of Ben Johnson play or something, or a Moliere play.
He's the kind of person who, if he got an email from someone saying, I need your passbook details and £100,000, please send it here, he would do it.
Yeah.
So there was an Abbe who'd been at the seminary with him, but you know, when they were young, who remembered him as haughty, inconsiderate, unreasonable, spendthrift, not very bright, fickle in his tastes and his friendships.
But...
But as I say, he does have two good qualities.
He's very generous and, Dominic, he's an Anglophile.
Trying to smell.
So these are positives.
Yeah, I wouldn't hear a word against him.
The problem is, though, that he has infuriated Marie Antoinette.
Marie Antoinette hates him.
And the reason for that is he'd gone to Vienna as ambassador.
And because he's an Anglophile, he doesn't really like the Austrians.
And he's always writing rude letters about Maria Theresa, Marie Antoinette's mother, to his confidants at Versailles.
And one of them reads out something rude he said about Maria Theresa.
And it gets back to Marie Antoinette.
So she's very upset about this.
And he's also gone around, when he comes back from Vienna, he's in Versailles.
He loves a bit of gossip.
He's not very bright.
He goes around accusing Marie Antoinette of having an affair with the Comte d'Artois, the younger brother.
It's very reckless of him.
Yeah, very.
I mean, it's mad.
And also he says of the Queen, she displays a coquettishness that prepares the way for an accomplished lover to succeed with her.
I mean, mad.
Yeah.
Well, just...
I mean, yeah, he's foolish and he lets his tongue run away with him, clearly.
And people who've seen Dangerous Liaisons or read the book, the book by Laclau, written at exactly this period.
I mean, this is exactly what's going on.
It's people kind of gossiping about each other, overhearing it, reading letters that aren't meant for them, all this kind of thing.
So it's absolutely part of the climate.
But the Cardinal de Rohan is not smart enough, really, to profit from it.
And so he's distraught.
He's distraught that he feels that now that Marie Antoinette is standing in the way of him getting the kind of promotion that he feels should be his right as a Rohan.
So he'll do anything to try and get her back.
And it's at this point that an impecunious woman with a sob story approaches him.
Yeah.
And this is a woman called Jeanne de Lamotte.
And she claims descent from the Valois, who are the traditional royal family who kind of gone extinct in the 16th century.
But that's obviously just...
Replaced by the Bourbon.
That's obviously just rubbish to appeal to the Cardinal, isn't it?
I mean, she's a swindler.
Well, this is the story.
This is her story.
And she approaches the Cardinal for some charity, which the Cardinal gives her.
And almost certainly they have an affair.
How does that work?
I'd like some charity, please.
Oh, my dear.
I've got some charity upstairs.
Come through.
I think that's exactly how it works.
Right.
I think that's...
Yeah.
So the Cardinal is a notorious womanizer.
And the Cardinals in the Ancien Régime tend to be.
They've got to be by law, surely.
So having done that, Lamotte then thinks, do you know what?
I'm going to aim higher.
And she wants to get...
Amazingly, she wants to get quarters in Versailles.
And so she persuades the Cardinal to introduce her to one of the sisters of Louis XVI.
And Lamotte has prepared for this moment very, very skillfully.
So she's introduced to the sister of Louis XVI.
And she faints.
She's kind of overcome.
And whether this is staged or whether it's real, I mean, who knows?
But the consequence of this is that she is seen as an unfortunate who has suffered terrible things
and therefore needs to be helped.
And this plays into the spirit of kind of sentimentality and sensibility that is absolutely kind of current
and associated with Marie Antoinette and her kind of vibe at Versailles.
And so she gets these quarters.
And she then starts using this.
She starts telling the Cardinal that she's become great friends with the Queen herself.
I mean, the Queen does have her...
You referred to that in the last episode as her squad.
So it's not that impossible.
I mean, it could happen that she could become...
So the Cardinal completely believes it.
And Lamotte then starts saying, you know, the only way to get to Marie Antoinette's heart is to buy her the most notorious necklace in France.
It had been made by the court jewelers.
It's Burma and Bassange who had been commissioned by Louis XV to make this.
It's called kind of slave necklace because it looks like a kind of collar that a slave might wear.
It consists of 647 diamonds and these weigh 2,800 carats.
So, I mean, it is massively vulgar.
Yeah.
And so Jonathan Beckman describes it as grotesque and almost literally unbearable.
It more resembled an item of chain mail or something a monk might wear in penitential self-chastisement than a coveted piece of jewelry.
It's a necklace that...
That Donald Trump would buy for a lady of the night.
Yeah.
Yes.
For a porn star, perhaps.
Particularly if he was trying to quieten her.
And unfortunately, the jewelers had never been able to give this to Madame du Barry because Louis XV had died.
And so, therefore, Madame du Barry had been chucked out of Versailles and wasn't in a position to buy it.
And so they're stuck with this enormous bill and they need to sell it to someone.
And so the obvious person is Marie Antoinette.
So they keep saying, you know, would your majesty, would you like to buy this?
And it's not Marie Antoinette style at all.
I mean, it's kind of vulgar.
I think it's nature and simplicity and like, you know, curl, falling curls and no corsets and all that stuff.
And on top of that, of course, it had been made for Madame du Barry.
So it kind of, you know, it's not just vulgar.
It has associations with kind of courtesans.
Yeah.
So absolutely not her.
And also she has been warned by both her mother and her husband, the king, you know, to stop displaying the bling, that it's not going down well.
And also Monsieur Léonard, who we talked about, the hairdresser, he has been phasing jewels out from her hairstyle, going for the natural look, the flowers.
So basically it's not her thing at all.
She does not want it.
So you might think, well, you know, couldn't the cardinal have done some cursory research on this?
And he'd have realized this is a mad thing.
Marie Antoinette would never have wanted this necklace.
But it's at this point, Dominic, that another figure steps into the story.
And this is someone.
This is someone you're very keen on, isn't it?
It's an Italian occultist called supposedly the Comte de Cagliostro.
Yeah.
So his story is enough to take up multiple podcasts, but just to absolutely condense it.
He told multiple different stories.
Some of them he said he was the son of the master of the Knights of Malta or a bigwig from Egypt or from an Ottoman pasha.
There were stories that he was 300 years old.
No, even longer.
He was 3,000 years old.
3,000 years old.
Yeah.
There are stories that he'd been at the wedding in Cana in the Bible with Jesus and co.
Basically, what seems to be the truth is that in reality, either he was born in Sicily in the slums of Palermo to a Jewish family,
or he's the son of a coachman from Naples.
We don't know which.
He seems to have had time as an apprentice hairdresser.
Yeah, a lot of hairdressers behaving badly.
And then he basically becomes a swindler, a professional charlatan.
He goes around.
He says he's dreamed up in a special Egyptian form of freemasonry.
He's got a fake countess wife, and she sells the package basically to aristocratic ladies.
And he seems to have come into contact with the cardinal in Strasbourg in 1781.
And the cardinal, as you said, Tom, is an absolute flipping dupe.
Yeah.
I mean, that's what the whole thing about being a character from Moliere play.
And he believes all this stuff about freemasonry on the occult.
He believes that Cagliostro is an alchemist.
And there are stories, aren't there?
And I think they're probably not true, but there are stories that Cagliostro was in on the plot and held seances and occult rituals to persuade Roanne, the cardinal de Roanne, that the stuff about the necklace is true and that this is the way to Marie Antoinette's heart.
And, of course, the thing is with always with confidence tricks is that people have to want desperately to believe that what they're being told is the case.
And it's not just the cardinal who wants to believe.
The jewelers do as well, because they want to recoup their investment.
So November 1784.
So this is a few months after the meeting in the gardens at Versailles.
The cardinal gets a letter that has been signed, Marie Antoinette de France, which is a signature she would never use because that's not diplomatic at all.
And the cardinal, as a former diplomat, should have known this, but he doesn't.
And in this letter, he gets informed that.
The cardinal is to acquire the necklace for the queen and that the queen will pay for it in four installments.
So brilliant.
The jewelers are delighted.
The cardinal is delighted.
You know, this is his way back.
So on the 29th of January 1785, the jewelers give the cardinal the necklace.
A courier then arrives, who claims to be from the queen.
The cardinal gives the necklace to this courier.
What a fool that cardinal is, Tom.
I mean, unbelievable.
Do you think it's the courier, Dominic?
It's not.
No, who is it?
Tell me.
Tell us who it is.
Surprise us.
It's one of Lamotte's lovers.
Yeah, you astound me.
And he goes away.
He gives it to Lamotte's husband.
So that's very, very marquis de Sade.
Lots of.
So the husband then breaks it up and he starts trying to fence the diamonds around Paris, but it's obviously dangerous to be doing it in Paris.
So he then goes to London and starts doing it there.
Meanwhile, of course, the jewelers are waiting for their money.
Yeah.
And the cardinal.
The cardinal is waiting for signs of the queen's favor that he's been promised.
And he goes to court and he's kind of waiting to see the queen with the necklace.
Absolutely nothing.
So early July, he thinks, you know, I've got to see what's going on.
So he sends Marie Antoinette a discreet note, kind of saying, very much looking forward to seeing these, you know, you know, wink, wink, you know what I've got you, eh?
Nudge, nudge.
Yeah.
And Marie Antoinette thinks he's mad.
Yeah, of course.
He just disposes of the letter.
Of course.
Early in August, the jewelers are so desperate, because they're now facing bankruptcy, that they go to one of Marie Antoinette's ladies-in-waiting and say, look, where's this money that the queen promised us?
And they go to the queen and she, you know, she's got no idea that any of this has been going on.
And Marie Antoinette leads the investigation.
Personally, understandably, she's appalled.
I mean, she's completely innocent.
And yet her good name has been consistently abused throughout the entire affair.
And she has this kind of dramatic declaration of purpose.
Hideous vices must be unmasked.
The purple of a cardinal and the title of a prince have cloaked a money grabber, a fraudster who dares to compromise the wife of his sovereign.
France and all of Europe shall know of it.
And so she goes to the king and the king issues orders that the cardinal be arrested.
And so he is on the 15th of August.
And he is arrested while he is celebrating.
He's holding mass to celebrate the Ascension of the Virgin in the chapel at Versailles.
He's in his full robes, you know, smoke, bells, the works.
In come the king's guards.
He's arrested and taken off to the Bastille.
Crikey, Tom.
What a story this is.
Napoleon Bonaparte in later life said that the death of Marie Antoinette began at the trial of the diamond necklace conspirators.
And Tom?
That's a big claim from Napoleon.
I mean, who am I to argue with Napoleon?
He was there.
Why would one say that of something that on the surface seems a little bit inconsequential and, of course, in which the queen is not really involved?
Right.
Because, I mean, I guess people said, well, of course, the French Revolution, a scandal about a necklace would be low down the list.
Very low down the list, yeah.
Bread riots, fiscal incompetence, all kinds of things, which we will be looking at in due course.
I think that the answer to why it is so damaging to the queen is the way that the scandal comes to be teased out and the way that it goes public.
Yeah.
So what happens is that all the main participants in the scandal, so the cardinal, Nicole, aka the Baron d'Oliva, the Comte de Cagliostro, and, of course, de la Motte, they're all arrested.
And they're all brought to court.
They're all brought to trial.
And the trials that they have are open.
So, you know, the proceedings can be reported.
And so this means that the queen had said all of France and Europe shall hear of this.
This is exactly what happens.
But it doesn't work to her advantage.
Well, just on that, so the openness.
I think it's important that people get a sense of what an enormous appetite for news and gossip there is in Paris in particular in the 1780s.
So we mentioned earlier Robert Darnton's brilliant book.
Revolutionary Temper.
And he talks in that about how all the different lawyers, we mentioned this, didn't we, in the first half, Tom, that the different lawyers of the various participants publish these, what they call these memoirs of the case, while the case is going on.
And these would go through multiple editions and they would sell tens of thousands of copies.
And people would literally read them out in cafes and people would gather to read them together.
It's a kind of collective experience of the news and of rumor and gossip.
And this case is the perfect story for all that.
And it actually ties together all these anxieties and sort of fantasies about Marie Antoinette that have been gathering pace for more than a decade.
Go on, Tom.
And I think a kind of parallel, the closest parallel I can think of from modern times would be the way in which the failure of the marriage of Prince Charles and Diana kind of exploded.
There was gossip about it.
There were whisperings about it.
There was talk about it.
And then suddenly it was all brought together.
It was brought out into the open.
And there was this absolute kind of firestorm of obsession.
And I think that that is basically what happens.
And it's devastating for Marie Antoinette and for the Crown generally because all the protagonists in various ways come to be exonerated.
Three of them are legally exonerated.
Four of them are kind of basically exonerated before the bar of public opinion.
And so the Crown is left completely baffled and perplexed.
And wounded by this.
So to go through the various, you know, the participants in these trials, three of them, all of whom have been sent to the Bastille.
And to be sent to the Bastille in this period, you know, to go to the Bastille, the Bastille is the symbol of royal oppression.
So it kind of immediately makes them heroes.
People are instinctively on their side.
So the Cardinal, when he goes to the Bastille, he is improbably cast as a kind of victim of royal oppression.
He becomes the people's Cardinal.
But the thing is, Simon Sharma says in Citizens, he actually moved into a specially furnished apartment outside the prison where he spent nine months entertaining a stream of distinguished visitors.
Oysters and champagne were laid on as a collation for guests.
And the Cardinal was allowed choice works from his library and a retinue of servants to help him overcome the hardships of incarceration.
But the image is that there are, you know, dripping water and clanking chains and rats and straw and everything.
But it's not at all like that.
Yeah.
And he says that he doesn't want the King to try it, basically because he doesn't trust the King.
And so he says he wants to go to the Parlement de Paris.
And the Parlement isn't, it's not a parliament.
It's kind of like the High Court.
Yeah.
And so he goes on court there.
It's open.
And the lawyer, his lawyer presents him as, you know, a kind of Rousseau-esque figure.
A figure, you know, who has, you know, an excess of candor.
He's at one with nature.
Yeah.
You know, he's not suited to the machinations of a corrupt and decadent court.
He's Mother Nature's child.
Right.
All that kind of thing.
Yeah.
And also, you know, he just wanted to serve the Queen.
It was his chivalrous duty.
He's been made a fool of in this story, but he's not a conspirator.
I mean, he's not a criminal.
No.
So they were right to acquit him.
So there is a measure of truth there.
Yeah.
And so he does get acquitted.
But the implications of this are devastating for Marie Antoinette and Jonathan Beckman.
And I think that's what the statement spells it out.
Louis and Marie Antoinette could scarcely believe that the Parlement had, in effect,
ruled that the Queen could be mistaken for the kind of woman who might arrange a midnight
assignation by a ruinously expensive necklace without her husband's permission and correspond
in secret with a known roué.
Right.
Because if you're assuming that he could be easily fooled, then you're assuming that
the possibility exists that she could have behaved like this.
And then we know, you and I know.
And everybody who's read the books on her knows that she would never have behaved like
this.
But the French public have been primed to think that she might.
Yeah, absolutely.
And he retires to Strasbourg, where he's greeted as a kind of an oppressed innocent.
Yeah.
So that's him.
Nicole, the Baron d'Oliva, the account that we gave, as we said, is that's basically
derived from the lawyer that she has.
Who essentially casts her as the kind of heroine of a novel.
And if it sounded like a novel, then I think there may be kind of element of that.
But I think the basic outline of what happened is true, but clearly it's been kind of slightly
enhanced.
I mean, she is a victim of it, really.
I think she is.
She's been made a tool.
She is.
She's been made a dupe of.
Yeah.
And what makes people even more sympathetic is that in the Bastille, she's given birth
to a baby.
So that makes her even more of a kind of sentimental heroine of a Rousseau novel.
Yeah.
The Comte de Cagliostro.
He's a great character.
I mean, he has a...
So in the Bastille, he continues to play the part of the Magus, the man who is 3,000 years
old.
So there's this brilliant detail in the interrogation in the Bastille.
He's asked, do you have any regrets about the life that you've led?
And Cagliostro replies, yeah, I feel terrible about the assassination of Pompey the Great
and my role in that.
Pompey the Great, you know, the great rival of Julius Caesar, had been killed 2,000 years
before.
So that's brilliant.
But once he gets to his trial, he immediately switches around and suddenly casts himself
as a kind of cool enlightenment sceptic.
And he gets asked by the prosecution lawyer, why do you say that you're thousands of years
old?
And he says, I'm not.
I'm 37.
Yeah.
So lots of the stories about Cagliostro, to be fair, come from pamphlets about him rather
than things himself.
So the Pompey the Great story.
I mean, he probably either said it as a joke or didn't say it.
I mean, anyway, he's a good character.
I like him.
And actually the government accounts, which was by a barrister called Target, and which
was in it, he wrote a memoir and it was the sort of government approved one, basically
said, Cagliostro had nothing to do with this at all.
He was like dragged in as exciting window dressing, but he wasn't really in it.
He was apparently in Lyon when the whole thing was taking place anyway.
So he probably...
Difficult to know because there are so many kind of rival...
He's such a fraud.
Yeah.
You can trust anything that he says.
No, that's true.
So it's difficult to know.
But I mean, anyway, he gets off.
I mean, people agree that he doesn't have anything to do with it.
As for Jeanne de la Motte, the confidence trickster, she is convicted.
The evidence against her is overwhelming.
I mean, she's basically banged to rights.
But amazingly, even she wins public sympathy.
And she does this by essentially her defenses that everything that she said was true.
That Marie Antoinette was guilty, that she had wanted the necklace, that she had written
loads of letters, that she was in Versailles.
So she gets sentenced to life imprisonment in the Solpêtrière, which is, it's a kind
of former munitions factory, isn't it, that is notorious as the place where prostitutes
get sent.
It's basically a prostitute's prison.
So she gets taken there and she hasn't been told before the sentence is read to her.
What she's going to suffer.
So she's taken to the prison.
It's read out to her.
She's told that she's going to be birched, branded and be imprisoned for life.
And she goes absolutely ballistic.
She starts kind of scratching and writhing.
She bites a chunk out of the executioner.
She kind of swallows his flesh, so it is said.
And she's pinned down and the branding iron has V on it for voleurs, for thief.
One of the brands is successful.
It's really imprinted.
But the other one, she's twisting so much that it burns her breast and this kind of
stench of roasting meat.
So very, very horrible.
She's then taken inside.
She's given a kind of pudding bowl.
So all her hair is chopped off and then she is put into a rough gray Hessian dress and
locked up.
And amazingly in 1787, so only a couple of years later, she escapes.
And immediately it's assumed that this is all part of conspiracy, that the queen wants
her out of the way.
And then there may be an element of the fact, I mean, I don't know.
Maybe it's possible.
Who knows?
Anyway, she gets to London and when she's there, she writes this venomously slanderous
attack on the queen.
She claims to have had a sapphic relationship with Marie Antoinette.
She describes midnight assignations with the queen.
Heavens.
I found her so beautiful.
I said to myself, it is the goddess Flora toying with a humble little flower.
So the idea of, again, of Marie Antoinette as predatory, as, as, as domineering has groomed
her.
It's groomed her.
Yes, exactly.
And Chantal Thomas says, says of her, she was the Justine of the pre-revolutionary epic
by, and Justine is the heroine of the Marquis de Sade's most famous novel.
And the Justine is, is impeccably virtuous and because she is virtuous, she is persecuted
by the, the kind of Sardian.
Sardian monsters, the aristocrats.
And essentially this is, you know, if, if, if, if she is the Justine, then Marie Antoinette
is a kind of Sardian monster.
Yeah.
Simon Sharma says she represented herself as an orphan of an older France, a heroine
from the sticks, an innocent gone astray.
That's the same point, isn't it?
That the corrupting, she's an innocent rather like the Nicole, the person who she is actually
corrupted, ironically.
But in this case, she has been corrupted personally by Marie Antoinette.
And of course that may seem completely bonkers because we know, as you discussed so brilliantly
in the last episode, Tom, that Marie Antoinette is actually quite, she's not puritanical,
but she's very bourgeois in her.
No, she, I don't think she's bourgeois, but I think she, I mean, she's a kind of, she's
a combination.
I mean, she's Catholic and she's Rousseau.
You know, right.
Right.
She's a combination of kind of old school Catholic morality combined with a kind of
girlish giddiness, a kind of love of the country, of flowers, of-
Yeah.
But what she isn't is she is not a predatory lesbian sort of groomer of little girls or
young women or whatever that this woman is claiming.
But the problem is that these are portrayals of her that have already gained traction,
that she's a monster of extravagance.
And that she's a kind of predatory whore.
And the reason this scandal is so devastating is both that it amplifies those stories and
that it makes them kind of very, very public.
And so in the wake of it, you start to get that the portrayal of her as a kind of monstrous
nymphomaniac is completely turbocharged.
So by 1789, and we all know what happens in 1789.
Pamphlets.
A pamphlet is published, which describes her sexual record.
Nobility, clergy, third estate.
So this is the backdrop to the meeting of the three estates, which we'll be doing in
due course.
So it's obviously inspired by it.
Any man has a right to her favors.
The most handsome and robust are the most welcome.
Guards, lackeys, actors, height of opprobrium.
Oh, indelible shame.
So kind of loving it.
And it's not just the queen who gets caught up on this.
So also does her female favorites.
So this is when the stories about the Duchess de Polignac, who we talked about yesterday,
one of her squad, they get vituperative as well.
I mean, Duchess de Polignac is relatively harmless.
So is the Princess de Lambelle.
But they are both cast as kind of co-vampires in Marie Antoinette's nymphomaniac cover.
Queens of vice, Tom.
Queens of vice.
Absolutely.
And what's fascinating.
When you get to the moment of Delamotte, you start to get fantasies in which Marie Antoinette
and her favorites suffer similar punishments.
So a lampoon is published against the Duchess de Polignac.
And it kind of says, let's see her humiliated.
Let's see her punished.
Let's see her suffer before the gaze of the people.
Yes, madam, you must do penance.
And as the choice is up to the confessor.
Here is the penance.
I impose in the name of the nation, shave your head, don a gray Hessian dress as your
only adornment and go to the august assembly of the estates general in this garb to make
atonement and deliver up any remains of your plundering.
So it's kind of working with, you know, the punishments of convicted prostitutes.
And also the Austrian-ness is really important here, isn't it?
Because there are two claims additional to this.
One that's very common is that she actually, her first victim, as it were, or the first
person who perhaps groomed her.
Yes.
Was her own brother, the Austrian emperor, Joseph the second.
Yeah.
And of course.
So to pursue the note, the Mozart thing, he's the too many notes king.
Yeah.
Yes.
Um, but then the other thing is of course, that if she is Austrian, then she must, she's
not French and she must therefore be a traitor.
And the more that the international temperature kind of rises, uh, especially once the revolution
has got going, the more people say, you know, she is not merely.
Um, sexually kind of depraved.
She's politically depraved and she must be, you know, in the course of her sapphic lusts,
she is taking absorbing secrets and passing on secrets to France's enemies.
Yes, exactly.
So, and there's a sense that, um, Maria Theresa, her mother has sent her as a kind of, uh,
to infect France with her villainy.
Um, so you may wonder, well, how does.
How does that work?
How on earth does Marie Antoinette cope with all this abuse?
And the truth is that she treats it all with kind of amused disdain.
So as early as 1775, she had been, she, she wrote to Maria Theresa, her mother saying,
uh, we're in the middle of a satirical song epidemic.
They have made some up about everyone at court, men and women alike, French licenses, even
extended to the king.
I myself have not been spared.
Although this country is fond enough of malice, the songs are so flat and in such bad taste
that they are successful, neither with the public nor high society.
So two things there.
One, she's only 20 years old when she says that.
So I always find the stuff about Mary Antoinette actually unbelievably repulsive.
I mean, I just think how anybody can, can, can, I mean, how you can take the side of
the pamphleteers and not of the, basically the, the girl stroke young woman at the center
of them is beyond me.
But the other interesting thing is that she is quite wrong about that.
So when she says successful, neither with the public nor high society, she is dead wrong.
They are enormously successful.
And a lot of people.
Yeah.
If you say it often enough.
People will believe it.
Yeah.
And so Chantal Thomas in, um, uh, her wonderful book about the pamphlets and Mary Antoinette's
relationship to them.
I mean, she basically says that the, one of the reasons perhaps why they don't impinge
on Mary Antoinette is that she, she simply doesn't understand the power of the, of the
written word that she doesn't read.
Yeah.
She doesn't, she doesn't really read.
And she, she says, Mary Antoinette had nothing to learn from the outside world.
The hot headed, vehement words of the pamphlets were incomprehensible to her.
And so failed to touch her, but there, you know, there are expressions of, of public
hostility that, that do, that do have an impact.
So in, um, in May, 1785, and this is, you know, when the, the, the, the scandal is kind
of really building up, she goes into Paris and the people there refuse to cheer her.
And two years later, she's being booed and hissed on the streets of Paris.
Well, Tom, you say that, but actually Theo, our producer would tell you that she's not,
people aren't booing and hissing.
They are shouting out, ooh, ooh, and gee, gee, gee.
That's it.
It's their equivalent of hissing.
Yeah.
That's French for boo.
Yeah, exactly.
Um, and so the, um, the, you know, one of the, the, the chiefs of police in Paris writes
to the king at Versailles and says that the queen shouldn't go into the Capitol.
It's unsafe for her.
And so the Louis the 16th passes this onto his wife and forbids her to go to Paris.
And um, you know, Mary Antoinette is deeply, deeply wounded by this.
And so she cancels her public engagements in the Capitol.
And she basically retreats to the Petit Trianon, which of course then only makes the stories
because you know, why, what's she up to in there with all her, you know, her girlfriends
and yeah, terrible.
And the, I, the irony is of course, she cannot win that.
She's in a position now where whatever she does will be seen as evidence of guilt.
So ironically, the fact that she tried to be less formal than the court is seen that
she's not, you know, she's not a good queen.
The fact that she's with her, she's got her group of friends.
She's a lesbian.
You know, all of that.
All of the fact that she's not going into the city because she's being booed.
That shows she's arrogant and she doesn't care about the people and a traitor, you know,
she cannot win.
It's I feel really sorry for her.
And so you may wonder, well, does this matter, you know, does any of this matter?
It's just surface froth.
It does matter because it doesn't just damage the queen.
It also, the whole scandal of the, of the diamond necklace has also seriously for the
first time damaged the public reputation of the king.
You know, again, there have been kind of rumors bubbling under.
The surface, but again, it is this trial that brings slanders against the king to the surface.
And there are two things that they focus.
The first is that he is cast as a despot.
You know, he is the man who has sent all these people to the Bastille.
He's a monster.
He's a, he's an autocrat who doesn't respect the liberty of the people.
And as we'll see next time that has enormous traction because of the political and financial
crisis that France finds itself in.
It does.
And the tragedy is, is in a way the king has kind of absorbed some of the lessons.
So he, his treatment of Beaumarchais, who has written a preface to one of his plays
that the king interprets as being an attack on him.
He orders Beaumarchais to be arrested, but this time he doesn't send him to the, to the
Bastille.
He sends him to the, to a prison called the Saint Lazare, which is a correction center
for delinquent boys.
You know, where they're, you know, taught the error of their ways and kind of given
the birch and things like that.
And everyone finds this hilarious.
And so Beaumarchais who'd always had laughter on his side now finds that the laughter is
against him.
And basically his reputation is destroyed by it.
So it suggests the king is kind of learning how to play the game.
King, by the way, it's not a despot.
I mean, that's one thing that's really worth stressing.
If you think Louis XVI is a despotic Monarch.
I mean, you can, there are many things that Louis XVI gets wrong, but being too bloodthirsty,
too repressive.
Is definitely, I don't think there's any historian who would think that was one of
them.
Right.
And, and, you know, if he'd wanted to get to, if he'd been a real despot, the Cardinal
de Roja would have vanished and wouldn't have been sitting in his chambers, having kind
of capons.
But the other thing that, that this plays into is the, is the idea of the king as sexually
inadequate and more specifically now a cookhold.
Because if Marie Antoinette is cast as being this kind of voracious nymphomaniac, there
is this sense that she is.
Her powers are being drawn from the sexually inadequacies of the king.
And so you get all these, these, these rhymes about the size and the.
Yeah.
Rigidity or otherwise.
The flaccidity of, of the Royal member.
Yeah.
And in the kind of the, the account of the queen and the affair that de la mort writes
in London, she says that the Cardinal and the queen had been having an affair.
Yeah.
that they had been engaged in a conspiracy to make the cardinal um the prime minister of france and
to uh subject france to the dominance of austria and so the king is somehow seen as being complicit
in this and so the the king and queen of france the emblems of the greatness of the country are
being cast as agents of an enemy power well robert darnton in his book the revolutionary temper
quotes a bookseller at the height of the diamond necklace affair who who wrote i think to in his
journal or to his uh his brother i can't remember which but he wrote the public spirit has turned
against him the king because he inspires no respect no fear no confidence and he throws
away the public's money for all sorts of follies and that you know that is the lesson that if you
are a slightly gullible reader of these pamphlets and this sort of these propaganda
kind of pornographic fantasies that's what you think about the king that as darnton says he's
well-meaning but stupid bewildered incompetent timid indecisive constantly drunk unfit even to
german to govern a german principality yeah absolutely and um darnton is brilliant on why
this matters um and and because essentially it's also going with the grain of the crisis
that france itself is confronting that um
this is a time where the state is running out of money and where people are starting to go hungry
there's been a succession of of terrible harvests and all this kind of stuff about diamond necklaces
and um cookholding and cardinals and all kinds of stuff it does actually matter because it gives
color and venom to what otherwise might be kind of the sense of inchoate forces that are going
wrong
yeah yeah absolutely it does and so i think important just to emphasize at this point
as we approach the fateful year 1789 that this is not about republicanism again so much of this
is coming from within the court so it's coming from the duc de provence the the king's young
brother um it's also coming from um the duke of orleans the duc d'orleans um who is the kind of the
after the the three royal brothers the most significant peer of the realm who has a whole
area of paris that is his private you know fiefdre the palais he's the palais royal and so he's
basically said anyone can publish what they like there and so it's become a hotbed of all these
kind of pamphlets and and stuff so there's that so it doesn't it absolutely doesn't imply
republicanism it's it's the science of an immunity system going down and it matters because basically
The whole body politic seems diseased.
And Dominic, I think in the next two episodes,
we're going to explore exactly, you know,
beyond the flower gardens of Versailles,
exactly how these diseases are kind of manifesting themselves
out in Paris and in the countryside.
So we'll be back on Thursday
and we will be looking at the crisis
that France finds itself in in the 17 ages,
the crisis that leads to the calling of the States General
and the beginning of the revolution.
So there'll be a bit of finance.
There'll be a lot of politics.
There'll be a lot of famine.
There'll be all of this kind of stuff.
Tennis courts.
There'll be tennis courts.
Of course, we'll be getting to the tennis court oath.
And then, of course, to the fall of the Bastille.
Very, very exciting.
A bientôt, à jeudi et au revoir.
Au revoir.